<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An apology for the ministers of the county of Wilts, in their actings at the election of Members for the approaching Parliament. In answer to a letter sent out of the said county, pretending to lay open the dangerous designes of the clergy, in reference to the approaching Parliament. Wherein is shewed, the notorious falshood of the said letter: how injurious it is to the gentlemen elected: and the dangerous designe of it against the ministry. By some of the defamed ministers of the Gospel in the same county. Humphrey Chambers, D.D. John Strickland. Adoniram Bifield. Peter Ince.</title>
            <author>Chambers, Humphrey, 1598 or 9-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78553</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1914</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E808_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207523</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866568</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866568</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118844</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78553)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118844)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 123:E808[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An apology for the ministers of the county of Wilts, in their actings at the election of Members for the approaching Parliament. In answer to a letter sent out of the said county, pretending to lay open the dangerous designes of the clergy, in reference to the approaching Parliament. Wherein is shewed, the notorious falshood of the said letter: how injurious it is to the gentlemen elected: and the dangerous designe of it against the ministry. By some of the defamed ministers of the Gospel in the same county. Humphrey Chambers, D.D. John Strickland. Adoniram Bifield. Peter Ince.</title>
                  <author>Chambers, Humphrey, 1598 or 9-1662.</author>
                  <author>Strickland, John, 1600 or 1601-1670.</author>
                  <author>Byfield, Adoniram, d. 1660.</author>
                  <author>Ince, Peter, b. 1614 or 1615.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ralph Smith, at the Bible in Cornhill, neer the Royall Exchange.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to "The copy of a letter sent out of Wiltshire, to a gentleman in London" by "A true friend to the publique interest, and to all peaceable men".</note>
                  <note>With a final advertisement leaf.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 12".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>True friend to the publique interest, and to all peaceable men. --  Copy of a letter sent out of Wiltshire, to a gentleman in London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain. --  Parliament --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Clergy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Wiltshire (England) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118844:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN APOLOGY FOR THE Miniſters of the County of Wilts, in their Actings at the election of Members for the approaching PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <p>In Anſwer to a Letter ſent out of the ſaid County, Pretending to lay open the dangerous Deſignes of the Clergy, in reference to the approaching Parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein is ſhewed,</hi> The notorious falſhood of the ſaid Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: How injurious it is to the Gentlemen elected: and the dangerous deſigne of it againſt the Miniſtry.</p>
            <p>By ſome of the Defamed Miniſters of the Goſpel in the ſame County.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Humphrey Chambers,</hi> D.D.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>John Strickland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Adoniram Bifield.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Peter Ince.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 6.8.</bibl> Then I ſent unto him ſaying, There are no ſuch things done as thou ſayeſt, but thou feigneſt them out of thy own heart.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5.</bibl> Therefore judge nothing before the time, untill the Lord come, who both will bring to light the hidden things of darkneſs, and will manifeſt the counſels of the hearts, and then ſhall every man have praiſe of God.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Ralph Smith,</hi> at the Bible in Cornhill, neer the Royall Exchange. 1654.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:118844:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118844:2"/>
            <head>An Apology for the Miniſters of the County of <hi>Wilts</hi> in their actings at the Election of Members for the <hi>Approaching Parliament.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough Chriſtians in generall, eſpecially the Miniſters of the Goſpel, muſt look and prepare for reproaches in this life, and may weare them as a crown of Glory, when they are unjuſtly caſt upon them; yet the Apoſtle <hi>Pauls</hi> often endeavours to quit himſelfe from ſleightings and ſlanders, that his Miniſtry might not be blamed or blemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed through him, ſeems to us a ſufficient warrant for any, Chriſtians or Miniſters, to ſeek to remove ſuch ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous imputations, as being openly and falſly raiſed againſt them, tend to the diſhonour of Chriſtianity, or Miniſtry, or both; eſpecially when the Actors in this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury are high pretenders to an extraordinary pitch of holineſſe, religion and piety; whoſe words may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore plead for credit where they come. This is an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy for appearing in print at this time, in Anſwer to a Letter lately printed and publiſhed, ſent out of <hi>Wiltſhire</hi> to a Gentleman in <hi>London,</hi> pretending to lay open the dangerous deſignes of the Clergy in reference to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching Parliament. This Letter pretended to be written to a friend in <hi>London,</hi> was intended and calcula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as we ſee by the haſty printing and publiſhing of it, generally for all <hi>England,</hi> publiquely to calumniate the Clergy and Gentlemen choſen to ſerve in the next Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament for the County of <hi>Wilts,</hi> and to prepare contempt and ſcorn for them in the hearts of all men, ſo far as the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118844:3"/>credit or cunning of the Compiler of this Letter could poſſibly prevaile for that end; yet it is ſaid to be written <hi>by a true friend to the publique intereſt and all peaceable men:</hi> to which we have not much to ſay, though the ſpirit of this Letter ſeem not to ſubſcribe the teſtimony which the writer thereof bears to himſelfe. But our main bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe is with the Letter it ſelfe, the dangerous deſigne whereof is manifeſt, <hi>viz.</hi> to render the Clergy (as he cals them) deſpicable in the eyes of the people, which wil more fully appeare in the Anſwer to the Letter it ſelfe. In which the Authour pretends to <hi>anſwer the expectation of the Gentleman to whom he writes, in giving a true account of paſsages relating to the chooſing of Members to ſit in Parliament for the County of Wilts;</hi> but how much he hath diſappoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the expectation of his friend, wil appeare to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Reader, when we ſhal have diſcovered the falſneſs both of his Narrative and Invective. It ſeems this man was very angry, and therefore quarrels with all that ſtand in his way, and ſome are apt to think it was becauſe himſelfe was not choſen, at leaſt becauſe his friends were paſſed by: and if this be true, the ingenuity of the <hi>Noble Theban</hi> that went home rejoycing that there were ſo many men fitter then himſelfe to ſerve the publike, would have ſaved him all this labour.</p>
            <p>We wil not ſo far prejudice that Noble Gentleman whom the Author of this Letter hath ſufficiently deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, and unworthily traduced, and whom by way of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour we ſhal name, Sir <hi>Anthony Aſhley Cooper,</hi> as to make any Anſwer to what is in this Letter charged upon him; he needs no Advocate in what he did, acting as we are confidently aſſured with a publique ſpirit, and deſirous to doe his Countrey reall ſervice. Nor wil we ſo far leſſen the eſteem of thoſe Gentlemen choſen in our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try to ſerve in the next Parliament, as to undertake their defence, againſt that reproach which is boldly and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally caſt upon them in this Letter; <hi>aetatem habent.</hi> We are much aſſured, having particular knowledge of the Religious integrity and eminent faithfulneſſe of many
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118844:3"/>of them, that they have no way deſerved that black ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny he ſeeketh to faſten upon them, as <hi>unworthy time-ſerving men, and ſuch as never did the State any ſervice. Si accuſaſſe ſufficiat, quis erit Innocens.</hi> Neither doe we know why this ſingle accuſer ſhould think ſo highly of htmſelf, as to expect that he ſhould bear down with the weight and warrant of his own Letter, the reputation of thoſe Gentlemen, whom their Countrey hath honoured, and in aſſurance of their fidelity entruſted with whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is dear unto them in this world. But ſince the Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of this Letter, (whether upon his own account, or with advice of others, we know not) is pleaſed to vent the heat of his indignation <hi>againſt the Clergie,</hi> as he is pleaſed to ſtile them, and to ſet ſome of us by name as <hi>ringleaders of the faction</hi> in the front of thoſe Miniſters of the Goſpel in this Countrey whom in his Rhetorick he cals a <hi>Scottiſh faction, Politique ſtate Parſons, a time-ſerving generation, ſelf-ſeeking Parſons, the corrupt Clergy, Rigid fooliſh men, a corrupt ſelf-ſeeking generation of men,</hi> and to bend all his forces againſt us and them, as carrying on <hi>ſome dangerous deſigne</hi> in our activity about this election of Members to the Parliament, concerning which he makes ſuch a horrible outcry: We conceive our ſelves bound in duty towards God, and for the upholding of the credit of our Miniſtery, ſo much reproached by him, to examine the Bil of high complaints laid in againſt us. The accuſation in which we with the reſt of the brethren of the Aſſociation are charged in this Letter, is either by way of <hi>Narrative,</hi> or <hi>Invective;</hi> and we ſhal anſwer unto both. By way of Narrative it is affirmed for truth, firſt, <hi>That the Ringleaders of this faction were, Dr. Chambers, Mr. Byfield, Strickland; theſe, with the reſt of the brethren of their Aſſociation gathered together a great number of people, and taught them their leſſon beforehand.</hi> To which we anſwer:</p>
            <p>Firſt, ſee how this man ſtumbles at the threſhold; the truth is, the firſt of thoſe mentioned in the Catalogue, his acting in the buſineſſe, except upon the day of election, was next to doing nothing in it: which we mention not
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118844:4"/>becauſe any of us know any cauſe why we or any other ſhould be either ſorry or aſhamed, of being more active therein; but the truth is, upon a preſſing occaſion he was out of this Countrey for above a fortnight together, and came not to his own houſe till the night before the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: and not to <hi>Wilton,</hi> till a great part of the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny were gone unto the Hil on the day, and at the time of the Election: and ſo it fell out by providence that he had not opportunity <hi>to gather together a great number of people,</hi> much leſſe <hi>to teach them their leſsons before hand:</hi> By this the <hi>Reader</hi> may ſee how little truth is to be expected in the reſt, when there is ſo groſſe an untruth in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning. And we ſee evidently, that the writer of this Letter watcheth for our halting, and beareth us ſo much good wil as to take us up before we be down.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſuppoſe it had been true of all the <hi>three Ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaders mentioned, with the reſt of their brethren,</hi> as it is more particularly charged upon one of them (who hath lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, though he be by name reviled with the title of Scribe and Phariſee, yet not to revile again, but to commit him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to him who judgeth righteouſly,) that they were <hi>active, and exceedingly beſtirred themſelves in that election, buſly intermedling with more then ordinary diligence and activity.</hi> What is their crime? how can they be truly charged as offenders, and over buſie intermedlers in that which concerns them not, who are members of the ſame Commonwealth with others, and therefore are as much concerned in the welfare thereof as any others: <hi>In the peace thereof we ſhall have peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it may be the crime is <hi>our more then ordinary diligence and activity:</hi> To which we anſwer, <hi>what we have now done? is there not a cauſe?</hi> Surely more then ordinary diligence and activity is very juſtifiable when the caſe is more then ordinary. Can we expect to ſee another Parliament, in which the Intereſt of all that is or ſhould be deare unto us in this world, as Chriſtians, and as Engliſhmen, can be more concerned then in this preſent Parliament? Nay, are there not a generation of men amongſt us, who are
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118844:4"/>acted by ſuch principles as do manifeſtly tend to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting of Law, deſtruction of Propriety, and the utter extinguiſhing of the Miniſtry of the Goſpel, and ſhall we ſit ſtil?</p>
            <p>Another Charge is,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>That we with the reſt of our brethren of the Aſsociation taught the people gathered together by us, their leſson beforehand, to cry up onely thoſe ten men named in our Liſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this we anſwer: That there was a Liſt given out of ten names, we ſhal not deny; neither do we know any juſt exception to be made againſt it; we are confident the compiler of this Letter would have found no hurt at all in it, if that Liſt which he abetted, and which many were brought violently to abet, had been owned by us, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by the Countrey in their election; ſo as that the fault was this, that we did not teach them to cry up their Liſt; but we demand any ſhadow or proof of this, <hi>that we taught the people to cry up onely thoſe ten men mentioned in that Liſt,</hi> which he cals <hi>ours,</hi> which yet twas no more ours then thoſe Gentlemen of the Countrey, who were alſo concerned in it with our ſelves. Nay, we doe with much confidence affirm, that it was often expreſſed to ſeverall men, that men were left to their free liberty, if they were not ſatisfied in any of the ten to put in any other fit per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons in their room, and accordingly ſome did take that liberty. Neither did we ever perſwade any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to adhere to any of the ten, further then upon the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral account of their fitneſſe to do their Countrey faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſervice, and that was in truth the depth of our deſign, that ſuch men, and ſuch onely might be choſen.</p>
            <p>Another charge is,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>That we did teach the people to brand others, as namely Lieut. Gen.</hi> Ludlow, <hi>Col.</hi> Eyres, &amp;c. <hi>(who were nominated by approved faithfull men in the Countrey) with the names of Anabaptiſts, Levellers, to render them odious to the generality of the judicious people, by theſe falſe and mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious imputations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> We do again demand proof of this charge, that any of us did ever teach any one <hi>to brand Lieut, Gen.</hi> Ludlow,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118844:5"/>
               <hi>Col.</hi> Eyres, <hi>&amp;c. with the names of Anabaptiſts, Levellers;</hi> we doe with confidence affirme, that as we did not our ſelves, ſo neither did we heare any other to put them into this dreſſe, till we found them ſo clothed in the Letter. But ſuppoſe that ſome did uſe thoſe expreſſions, will it follow that they were taught by us ſo to doe? we thinke the leaders of their party would not take it well if we ſhould charge upon them all thoſe reproachful, ſcornful, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viling ſpeeches, uttered by very many of their followers upon the place, againſt ſuch who might have expected better language from them. We expected upon the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of two in their Liſt, the Author would have given us the names of all the reſt in my Liſt, and not have left us to ſpell out the meaning of an &amp;c. and to defend our ſelves from branding with reproachful names, we know not who. It were no difficult work we think to finde out the reſt of the names in that Liſt; but ſince the Author of that Letter is pleaſed to conceal them, we will not further provoke him by the mention of them.</p>
            <p>It is true that Liſt was commonly called by the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny upon the place, the Anabaptiſts Liſt; becauſe the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in that Liſt did either conſiſt of ſuch, or ſome of the moſt notedſt ſticklers for it went under that denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and ſo it wil not be ſtrange, that there ſhould be frequent mention of the name Anabaptiſt: yet we doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain deny that we did brand any of them with thoſe names, Anabaptiſts, Levellers, or taught others ſo to doe: And thus the ground-work fails him; ſurely then thoſe other words, <hi>to render them odious to the generality of the judicious people by thoſe falſe and malicious imputations,</hi> muſt needs be left to ſtand alone, and ſignifie nothing; onely becauſe the words may be of good uſe if they be rightly applied, we ſhal borrow them, and retort them with much more clearneſs of truth.</p>
            <p>The Authour in this Letter hath branded the faithfull Miniſters of the Goſpel, not onely in this Countrey, but throughout the Nation with the titles of a corrupt Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, a corrupt ſelf-ſeeking generation of men; and divers
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118844:5"/>ſuch like reproachfull terms to render them odious to the generality of the judicious people by thoſe falſe and malicious imputations.</p>
            <p>Another charge, at leaſt inſinuated againſt us, is,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
               <hi>That ſome hundreds gave their voyces who were either Cavaliers, or elſe of inconſiderable eſtates, not worth</hi> 100 <hi>li. and therefore uncapable of chooſing by the modle of the eſtabliſhed govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Although the words may be as wel applied to thoſe that voted for his Liſt, and with as much truth, as to the other ſide; yet becauſe there is in this Letter nothing but what is intended either directly or by inſinuation to caſt an odium upon us: We ſhall therefore ſay that we do not know of any one perſon that came thither upon any of our requeſts or deſires, that is lyable to either of thoſe exceptions. And we doe again put the Authour to this faire iſſue, either to make proofe but of one ſo qualified as is mentioned, that was brought thither to give his vote, by us: or elſe to ſay, that he hath wronged us in this inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation.</p>
            <p>The next charge is more expreſſe,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> though it hath as little truth as any of the former. He ſaith, <hi>it was agreed upon at length that the ſeverall liſts ſhould be called one by one, and ſo put to the yea's or no's, without naming any other in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition with the former: but this order was violated by the Clergies party, by which means, through the inſtigation of the Scottiſh faction Lieut: Gen.</hi> Ludlow was put by.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Whereas he ſaith, <hi>it was agreed upon at length that the ſeverall Liſts ſhould be called one by one:</hi> the truth is, it was agreed upon at <hi>firſt,</hi> upon the firſt comming upon the place: But it is apparently falſe, <hi>that this order was purpoſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly violated by the Clergie party;</hi> for the truth was, though it was agreed on by the Sheriffe and thoſe Gentlemen that were about him, and neere unto him, yet we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident the agreement was not known unto the tenth man, when the queſtion was put. And upon this miſtake the generality did look upon the queſtion, as if there were a compatition, and ſo did cry up him whom they did moſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118844:6"/>affect and deſire; and it was ſome time before this miſtake could be rectified, which yet was as much endeavoured by thoſe whom he cals <hi>the Scottiſh faction,</hi> as by any of their party that appeared on the other ſide: ſo that the violation of this Order was only by a miſtake. And it is apparently falſe <hi>that by means of the violation of this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, through the inſtigation of the Scottiſh faction, Lieut. Gen. Ludlow was put by;</hi> for the truth is, he was put by for want of voyces. That that Noble Gentleman hath been ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to the publique, we ſhal not deny, or goe about to diminiſh his worth; yet we ſee no reaſon to ſubſcribe to that odious compariſon, <hi>as if he had been more ſervicea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the true intereſt of the State, then all the men that are cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, put them together.</hi> And we doubt not but the modeſty and ingenuity of that Gentleman is ſuch, that he will give them little thanks for putting him in the ballance alone againſt the ten, many of whom have been eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſerviceable in their places, and to whom the Lieut. G. <hi>Ludlow</hi> wil think it no diſparagement to give them the right hand of fellowſhip. Whether it were the deſire of that Gentleman to be mentioned for the place, is much queſtioned by ſome who pretend to know ſomething; it is ſtrongly ſuſpected that his name was made uſe of with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his conſent, to make way for others; and if this be true, ſurely he wil give them but little thanks for ther la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, in making uſe of his name to ſuch an end; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we are confident, ſo great an aſſertor of the liberties of the people cannot take it wel, to have his name made uſe of, to impoſe upon the people ſo as it ſhal be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a crime for any not to appeare for him.</p>
            <p>The next charge is, <hi>Theſe Politique State Parſons neglected the preaching of their Lecture at</hi> Sarum,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
               <hi>that they might bawle with open mouth no</hi> Ludlow, <hi>no</hi> Ludlow, <hi>till they were even hoarſe again; they choſe rather to ſpend their breath in decry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing honeſt men, then in preaching the Goſpel of the Lord Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The truth is, the Lecture at <hi>Sarum</hi> (which he not without ſome ſcorn cals <hi>their Lecture</hi>) upon the day, and at the time of the election, was for that time <hi>omitted,</hi> but
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118844:6"/>not as he ſaith <hi>neglected;</hi> there may be ſufficient juſtifiable reaſons for the omitting of the Lecture for a turn, which yet wil not amount to a neglect of it: and we ſuppoſe this was a juſtifiable ground for that omiſſion; The greateſt part of the Auditors were called to another ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial ſervice, in which they were very much concerned, which could not be done at any other time. It is <hi>neglected</hi> by thoſe, who when they have time and opportunity, doe not frequent it: and then it wil be eaſie to judge, who they be who doe neglect the Lecture at <hi>Sarum.</hi> This is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident, the Miniſters who are called to preach that Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, are far more ready to beſtow their pains in preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, then ſome of thoſe who are ſo forward to turn this ſingle omiſſion to our reproach, are to attend upon it; there is onely this difference, the Miniſters did once omit it, and thoſe men never come unto it.</p>
            <p>For that other part of the charge, <hi>That we did baule and cry with open mouth no</hi> Ludlow, <hi>no</hi> Ludlow, <hi>till we were even hoarſe again, chooſing rather to ſpend our breath in decrying honeſt men, then in preaching the Goſpel of the Lord Jeſus:</hi> We anſwer there was a neceſſity of decrying ſome, as wil appeare by what is confeſſed to be agreed upon, viz. <hi>That every one ſhould be put to their yeas and noes, without naming any other in competition with him:</hi> for we demand how it was poſſible for us to give our votes according to that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, when there were ſo many in nomination, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>decrying</hi> ſome. It is confidently affirmed that this courſe was agreed on by their own motion and deſire; and if that be true, let the world ſee how they deale with us; put us on a neceſſity of crying, and then beat us for crying: But he ſaith, <hi>we did decry honeſt men. An.</hi> That which was to be decryed at that time, was not who were honeſt men, but amongſt many honeſt men, who were moſt fit to ſerve in Parliament; ſurely the chooſing of one doth not at all neceſſarily queſtion the honeſty of him that is refuſed. Whereas he ſaith <hi>we choſe rather to ſpend our breath in decry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing honeſt men, then in preaching the Goſpel of the Lord Jeſus;</hi> we anſwer, this work we were then called to, was not <hi>to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118844:7"/>preach the Goſpel,</hi> but to <hi>chooſe members for the approaching Parliament;</hi> that was the work of the day.</p>
            <p>Beſides theſe partculars in the Letter by way of <hi>Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> relating to our ſelves, there are two paſſages in the letter relating to others, though charged obliquely upon our account, which are not to be omitted.</p>
            <p>The firſt in theſe words, <hi>What ſhall I ſay of the impudency of theſe men? One</hi> Stone <hi>a Factor for them, and a vaſsal to them, went up and down at the election like a mad man, crying out, Now friends appeare for the Church of God or never; poor man! can he put no difference between appearing for the luſts of men, and the Church of Chriſt? between the Claſſicall uſurpations of ehe ſelf-ſeeking Parſons, and the truth of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> By that perſon whom he reproachfully calleth <hi>one Stone,</hi> is meant Mr. <hi>William Stone of Sarum,</hi> a man of known ſufferings for, and fidelity to the publique, and whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity in point of Religion (for ought we know, or have heard of) is unblemiſhed. He deſired us to let the world know that neither the words aſcribed to him by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diter of this letter, nor any to the ſame purpoſe, were ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by him; howbeit he ſeeth no cauſe to extract, or bluſh at them, if he had ſpoken them; though he abhors the ſpiteful commentary which is made upon them; he knoweth very wel how to diſtinguiſh <hi>betwixt Chriſts Church</hi> and <hi>mens luſts,</hi> and wiſheth that diſtinction were better ſtudied, and held on all ſides; but as to the ſpeech fully aſcribed to him, he looketh upon it as a meer fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, invented to bring him in within the ſcrape, that he might have a ſhare in the reproach the writer of this let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was reſolved with his beſt skil to caſt upon the Clergy, and all that were friends unto them.</p>
            <p>The other perſonal charge is in theſe words: <hi>Sir, I had a ſight of a letter writ by one</hi> Burges, <hi>a perſon of the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracy, ſent to one of his brethren in this County: his words are as followeth: Sir, I hope you will be active to engage all that ever you can to appeare with us for ſuch men as will be valiant for the truth; and be ready to meet Dr.</hi> Chambers, <hi>Mr.</hi> Byfield, Strickland, Ince, <hi>&amp;c. and that we may not be divided, there
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118844:7"/>ſhall be a Laſt of the ten to be choſen given to every one that appeareth for the beſt intereſt; let us not be acceſſary to our own ruine, and give occaſion to the ſucceeding generation to curſe us, by not putting forth our intereſt to the utmoſt for chooſing right men. If we remember the laſt men that met at</hi> Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter, <hi>what they were voting by and withall, how the monſter of their malice was even brought to the birth, it will make us active for a better choice. Beſides what this Parſon writ in his letter, he told the party, before one Mr.</hi> Dyer, <hi>that there was a commiſſion comming out for ejecting Miniſters, and that he would be in danger of being outed his living, that ſhould not appeare with the Miniſters at the election.</hi> To this we anſwer.</p>
            <p>By that perſon whom he reproachfully calls <hi>one Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges a parſon of the confederacy,</hi> he meaneth Mr. <hi>Daniel Burgeſse,</hi> whom we look upon as a godly and able Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Jeſus Chriſt, but no <hi>Parſon of the confederacy;</hi> for we own no ſuch thing in his ſence: we are indeed in an <hi>aſsociation</hi> with many others of our godly brethren, in a way of <hi>Chriſtian communion,</hi> but not of a <hi>ſubtile combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> That the Author had a ſight of that Letter written by Mr. <hi>Burges,</hi> we will not deny; but we are aſſured that he hath not truly recited the ſaid Letter, as appeares by a copy of it, which we have under Mr. <hi>Burges</hi> his hand: his words in the cloſe of the letter are not as they are above recited, but as followeth: <hi>I pray you let us not be acceſſary to own ruine, and give the comming generation cauſe to curſe us, by not exerting our ſelves to the utmoſt for the chooſing of ſound and faithfull men: if we remember the laſt men that met at</hi> Weſtminſter, <hi>and what they were voting to ruine, have not we cauſe to adore that hand of providence that daſhed their deſigne (the monſter of their malice) when it was even come unto the birth, and now points us our to a better choice? the ſame Lord give us wiſdome timely to improve it.</hi> The inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Reader cannot but obſerve a conſiderable diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and ſo Mr. <hi>Burges</hi> is not obliged to own that letter as his, which his accuſer hath ſo mangled; yet becauſe he doth own it for the ſubſtance, we ſay that we ſee nothing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118844:8"/>in it, that would have turned to his reproach, if it had fallen into the hands of one that had been willing to give it a candid Interpretation. For theſe words ſo confidently affirmed to <hi>be ſpoken by Mr.</hi> Burges <hi>to the party before one Mr.</hi> Dyer, <hi>That there was a commiſſion comming out touching Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and that he would be in danger of being outed of his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, that ſhould not appeare with the Miniſters at the Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> Some of us have ſpoken with Mr. <hi>Burges</hi> and Mr. <hi>Dyer,</hi> and they confidently affirm the charge to be falſ through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and deny the words, ſo that we may well apply the following words unto the Author, <hi>The world may ſee how he maketh lyes his refuge, and hath recourſe to carnal wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides this <hi>Narrative,</hi> by way of <hi>Invective</hi> he char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth us,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>With being of the Scottiſh faction, and promoting of the Scottiſh intereſt.</hi> To this we anſwer:</p>
            <p n="1">1. In general, that we can the better beare their bitter revilings, becauſe the moſt eminent ſervants of God in their generations, after whom we are not worthy to be named, <hi>Luther, Calvin,</hi> and others met with the ſelf-ſame uſage, not only from Popiſh Adverſaries, but even many who pretended to higher attainments in religion, ſcorned, derided, and loaded them with reproach: Doubtleſſe the <hi>Goſpel</hi> would have leſſe <hi>Reproach,</hi> and the <hi>Profeſſors</hi> thereof more love amongſt them, if at the length theſe Scripture rules might obtaine place and practice in good earneſt, amongſt thoſe that name the name of Chriſt: <hi>Let us not judge one another any more, but judge this rather, that no man put a ſtumbling blocke or an occaſion to fall in his brothers way.</hi> And againe, <hi>Let all bitterneſſe, and wrath, and anger, and clamour, and evil-ſpeaking be put away from you with all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice.</hi> But to come more particularly to the ſharpe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vective againſt us.</p>
            <p>Theſe words, <hi>Faction, Intereſt,</hi> and <hi>Scottiſh</hi> joyned with them, are words of late much come into uſe amongſt us, but of that ambiguity, when they are uſed by way of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vective, that few can tell the meaning of them, it lying in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118844:8"/>the breſt of him that doth impoſe them upon others, to expreſſe in what ſenſe he meanes them; and therefore till the Author ſpeakes out what he intends by this charge, we ſhall only ſay at preſent: that when there hath been ſo much blood unhappily ſhed betwixt the Profeſſors of the Goſpel in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> it ſavoureth not much of a <hi>Chriſtian ſpirit,</hi> now that there is a hope of a <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> betwixt the Nations, to foment a perpetual <hi>enmity</hi> betwixt them, by making <hi>Scottiſh</hi> ſtill a proverbial ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of what is <hi>evil.</hi> What we can probably imagine to be his meaning in this Invective, will be fully anſwered in the examination of ſome of theſe Invectives that follow.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He doth charge us, that <hi>we make the oppreſſion of Tythes and fat Benefices our great</hi> Diana, <hi>which makes us in buſineſſe ſo active to uphold them.</hi> To this we anſwer.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Whether we doe make <hi>Tythes,</hi> and <hi>worldly gaine,</hi> and <hi>fat Benefices our great Diana,</hi> the accuſer we are ſure cannot tell; poſſibly we may be of another frame of ſpirit before the Lords eyes, then we are before his; certainly it would ſavour more of a Chriſtian ſpirit to leave <hi>ſecret things to the Lord our God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, What crime is it to deſire to <hi>uphold</hi> and <hi>enjoy</hi> the eſtabliſhed way of maintenance by <hi>Tythes,</hi> which for ſo many hundreds of yeares hath been ſettled upon the Miniſtry, both by Cuſtome and Law? We are very ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that there are many men juſtly chargeable with the ſin of <hi>covetouſneſſe,</hi> in reference unto Tythes. But then the compiler of this Letter ſhould doe well to conſider whether it be not more likely to be thoſe who covet to take them to themſelves when they have no right unto them, then thoſe who deſire but to enjoy their own by the ſame propriety that any man hath in his eſtate.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, For that maintenance ſettled by the Law of the Land upon the Miniſters of the Goſpel, we <hi>own it,</hi> and <hi>take it,</hi> in all <hi>Chriſtian freedome of ſpirit, bleſſing the Lord,</hi> who hath dealt with us in outward things <hi>beyond our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts or expectations;</hi> and we would aske the writer of the Letter a queſtion in his care; whether if he could get one
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118844:9"/>of thoſe fat benefices he ſpeakes of, ſettled by Act of State upon himſelfe and his poſterity, for his good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in decrying the Miniſtry, would he then take it for Idolatry or ſuperſtition to enjoy what he calls the <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of Tythes:</hi> this we are ſure is very evident in the practice of many that are the lowdeſt cryers againſt this intolerable oppreſſion, that they are content to liquor their fingers in it, and it is their greater griefe and burden that they may not keep that to themſelves, to which they can pretend no more right then a Tenant to detaine his Rent from his Landlord: And becauſe we are now upon the buſineſſe of Tythes, we ſhall examine another paſſage in the cloſe of the Letter relating thereunto. In thoſe words, <hi>This corrupt ſelf-ſeeking generation of men will not ceaſe from buſie intermedling in State matters and raiſing factions, till the maintenance of the Miniſtry be brought into one Treaſury, and equally divided. In</hi> Holland <hi>(you know) where the Magiſtrate takes a ſtrict account, the Miniſters dare not buſie themſelves thus in State-affaires.</hi> To this we ſay.</p>
            <p>Firſt, This is indeed a grand project, which ſome men pleaſe themſelves ſo much with, as that it is very proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble they have already laid out what place they ſhall get in this new office.</p>
            <p>Secondly, In this paſſage there is more then a hint of the grand intention of this deſigne of the <hi>common Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury for the Miniſters maintenance,</hi> viz. to make the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to be leſſe active and buſie, eſpecially in croſſing the wills of thoſe upon whom they are made to be ſo depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant; and if that be the intention of thoſe men, whom wt are charged to be ſo active in crying downe, we ſhall not need to ſay much to juſtifie our activity, eſpecially to all judicious men, who are ſenſible of the great miſchiefe t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at muſt needs come unto Religion, by ſuch a courſe, eſpecially when this diſpenſation of the Goſpel ſhall fall into the hands of ſuch who ſerve the Lord that they may ſerve their Bellies, and in order thereunto muſt ſerve the times, and therein the various luſts, humours, and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts of their maſters upon whom they doe depend. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118844:9"/>we doubt not but that if God have any plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in us, and delight ſtill to dwell amongſt us, he will reſerve a number <hi>that have obtained mercy to be faithful,</hi> who will not be turned out of their way by ſuch byaſſes of humane dependances, and if ever they ſhould be <hi>lead into that temptation,</hi> God will <hi>deliver them</hi> from the ſnare and the <hi>evil of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, How inconſiſtent is this project with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint before of the <hi>oppreſſion of Tythes?</hi> will that be leſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by taking them into a common treaſury? we doubt the Country man will not finde it ſo, when Tythes ſhall be required by more ſevere exactors then ever Miniſters were; So as that the world may ſee the eaſe of the people is not intended, no not by thoſe who make the lowdeſt cry of the oppreſſion of Tythes.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, He doth by way of charge againſt us, rank us with <hi>that ſort of men who have cauſed the late broyles in this Nation and</hi> Scotland, <hi>and who will not ceaſe plotting and combining till we imbroyle the Nation again in blood, if the Lord in mercy prevent not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We anſwer, we abhor the mention, either of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betting the former broyles, or of plotting and combining to imbroyle the Nations againe in blood; and we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the accuſer, to make good his charge as to any of us, or to lay aſide ſuch curſed provoking inſinuations againſt thoſe who deſire to be peaceable in the Land.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, We are charged to <hi>carry on a deſign to bring the Nation again into Egyptian bondage, and to ſet up our ſelves, &amp; our Claſſical</hi> Diana <hi>by civil ſanction, and to that end to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to procure a conſiderable number of Members that may vote in the next Parliament an Aſſembly or Convention of Miniſters to make Canons for the inthralling the conſciences of men, and to impoſe upon, and domineer over our brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Whether his friend to whom he writes, be as he ſayes, <hi>ſo conſiderate</hi> (that we ſay not ſo inconſiderate) as to <hi>obſerve ſuch a deſigne carried on by us with the reſt of the Clergy of this Nation,</hi> we cannot tell; but this is evident,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118844:10"/>himſelfe is ſo ſuſpicious, as that he can create Imaginary Plots and deſignes, and ſo uncharitable as to put the groſſeſt miſ-conſtruction upon an innocent action; and for our Innocency, we can appeal to God, and doe teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie in the preſence of the all-ſeeing God, that we deſire no ſuch power, nor affect no ſuch dominion over the conſciences of men; we tremble at and abhor the thought of it, knowing that it is beſt with the Church of God when men have leaſt to doe in making Lawes in it, and when they intend mainly the eſtabliſhing and obſerving of the Lawes of Chriſt the <hi>King of Saints;</hi> and if to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to his lawes, be with this man to be brought againe <hi>into Egyptian Bondage,</hi> ſurely though he ranke himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Saints, yet Jeſus Chriſt (we doubt) will ranke him amongſt thoſe who ſay <hi>we will not have this man to reigne over us:</hi> If there be a deſire in any to promote ſuch a ſettlement in matters of Religion as may be agreeable to the minde of Chriſt, and conſiſtent with the due liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of tender conſciences, we know not how that ſhould be accounted making Cannons to inthral the conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of men.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, We are charged that <hi>we will rather joyn with the vileſt of men, then with ſuch as croſse our carnal intereſts, and diſſent from us, though never ſo godly;</hi> and this he ſayeth <hi>he plainly ſeeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> For that of our <hi>joyning with the vileſt of men,</hi> we ſuppoſe he ſpeakes this in reference to the Election, and to our activity at it; and if ſo, we ſay, it is a moſt falſe and unchriſtian accuſation, and ſuch as could not have been faſtned upon us, by any diſcerning eye. But there is no ſenſe againſt the calumnies of men, foreſtalled with prejudice, and blinded with malice. It may be the pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of this Letter reckons all thoſe amongſt the <hi>vileſt of men</hi> that are not regiſtred in his Catalogue of Saints, and ſo would have dominion founded in grace and Saint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to be the only qualification for government. We deny not but it were much to be wiſhed that governours
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118844:10"/>might alwayes be endewed with grace and the knowledge of God in Chriſt, added to their other qualifications; but we cannot ſubſcribe to that principle which is truly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a <hi>State-hereſie</hi> by the Author of the true eſtate of the caſe of the Commonwealth in reference to the late eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed government, <hi>viz. That godly perſons though of ſmall underſtanding and little ability of minde in publick affaires, are more fit for government, then men of great knowledge and wiſdome, if endewed only with natural parts and moral ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues:</hi> But if our Author be not infected with that hereſie, we further anſwer, when he ſhall be pleaſed to tell us whom he doth meane by the <hi>vileſt of men,</hi> and in what act of ours he did <hi>plainly ſee our joyning with ſuch,</hi> we ſhall be able to give a better account by way of anſwer to him; and in the meane time if he have not too much worke upon him already to make good his other charges againſt us, we ſhall put him to that farther trouble, to name but any one of the ten that were choſen, whom we cryed up and voted for, that can in the leaſt give an occaſion to ſuch a charge; and in this he hath a double task to make good; one that the party is of the <hi>vileſt of men,</hi> and the other that we voted for him; and we are wel aſſured, he cannot make good either the one or the other. We liſt not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criminate, and deſire to avoyd all perſonall reflections; otherwiſe poſſibly there might be ſome juſt ground found to retort the charge, but we forbeare. Onely we deſire him ſeriouſly to conſider with whom <hi>he joyns</hi> in his ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring of the Miniſters of the Goſpel; ſurely this is the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of <hi>the vileſt of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For that other branch of the charge, our <hi>not joyning with thoſe who croſſe our carnall intereſts and diſsent from us, though never ſo godly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We anſwer, We doe ſo far honour, and prize, <hi>the power of godlineſſe,</hi> as that we ſhould be heartily glad to cloſe with ſuch in whom we finde it, in all waies of love and peace; it hath been our prayer, and ſhall be our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, that all who accord <hi>in fundamentals of Goſpel-truth
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118844:11"/>and holineſſe,</hi> may be brought to <hi>keep the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace;</hi> we hope (through mercy) we have learnt not to value our <hi>carnall intereſt</hi> before the <hi>Churches peace and unity;</hi> and to think and ſpeak of divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, emulations, and breaking into parties and facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, amongſt thoſe that are truly godly, as we doe think and ſpeak of theft, whordome, murder, and the like fruits of the fleſh. But yet we ſay,</p>
            <p>Firſt, we dare not under the ſpecious pretence of <hi>joyning with the godly party,</hi> cloſe with any who are, or ſeem to be ſuch, in actings of that nature, as are deſtructive, not ſo much to our <hi>carnall intereſt,</hi> as to the <hi>true intereſt of the glorious Goſpel of the bleſsed God:</hi> (for ſo we doe conceive the upholding of the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> and <hi>its maintenance</hi> is more the intereſt of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> then our own) leſt whilſt we ſeek to knit with men, we disjoyne our ſelves from God; and whilſt we would make up ſtrife with others, we make a greater breach between God and our own ſouls.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we ſee but little hope that ever there ſhould be a happy cloſure with thoſe who do ſo factiouſly <hi>engroſs</hi> all the honour of <hi>Saintſhip,</hi> yea <hi>honeſty and faithfulneſſe,</hi> to themſelves and their own party; for ſo the Author ſeems to carry it throughout the Letter. Himſelfe and his party he mentions as <hi>the poor deſpiſed Saints,</hi> as the <hi>appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved faithfull men in the County, honeſt publique ſpirited men, men that are moſt faithfull to the publique intereſt, ſuch as have been valiant in the field, and ventured their lives in the high places for the liberties of the people; ſuch as have all along in the greateſt revolutions and dangers appeared in their purſes and perſons for the true intereſt of the Nation, ſuch as have poured out floods of tears and prayers for the cauſe of Chriſt;</hi> But the reſt who doe oppoſe them, or not joyn with them, are called <hi>a Time-ſerving generation, a company of time-ſerving Cavaliers, and corrupt perſons, ſuch who in the greateſt Revolutions and Dangers durſt not ſhew their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, unleſſe it were at Oxon, where ſome of them ſate and acted;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118844:11"/>a company of unworthy time-ſerving men, ſuch as never did the State any faithfull ſervice, ſuch as doe unworthily and vain-gloriouſly in their own perſons hunt after worldy honour, and popular applauſe, and doe even hate and abhor the poore deſpiſed Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An.</hi> We would be loth to be juſtly ranked amongſt thoſe <hi>who doe hate and abhor the poor deſpiſed Saints;</hi> we deſire to love and honour them all, <hi>as the excellent ones in whom is our delight;</hi> yet we doe hate and abhor that curſed dividing principle, whereby <hi>Godlineſs</hi> and <hi>Saintſhip</hi> is made a <hi>faction</hi> with many; whilſt they incloſe and mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polize it unto themſelves and their own party, ſo as that none ſhall be counted <hi>Godly</hi> and <hi>Saints,</hi> owned, loved, and eſteemed as ſuch, but thoſe of their own way: we doe not doubt but that God hath many whom he will own as <hi>Saints,</hi> who yet are branded as <hi>carnall,</hi> nay as <hi>antichriſtian;</hi> And we could heartily wiſh, that even amongſt thoſe who are moſt forward to aſcribe and appropriate this title to themſelves, that there were more of <hi>Saintſhip</hi> to be found in them. The true Saints of God are indeed often <hi>deſpiſed</hi> and <hi>reproached</hi> by the men of the world; but it is certainly no evidence of Saintſhip to be <hi>deſpiſers</hi> and <hi>reproachers</hi> of their fellow brethren, and of any of the faithful Miniſters of the Goſpel: If the <hi>tree muſt be known by its fruits,</hi> how little Saintſhip ſhall we finde amongſt many of thoſe who yet doe ingroſſe all unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves?</p>
            <p>We ſhall not goe about to make our ſelves guilty of that which we have already condemned in the Author of this Letter, viz. <hi>making odious</hi> compariſons and deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of all that are not of our party; yet we are not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of this, either that all who did appear for that Liſt, for oppoſing whereof we are ſo much reviled, were <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved faithfull men, publique-ſpirited men, &amp;c.</hi> nor that they onely of that party were the <hi>onely honeſt, approved, faithfull, publique-ſpirited men in the County;</hi> being very confident, that there are very many in our County, who
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118844:12"/>though of a different perſwaſion in matters of Religion, from the Authour and his party he ſo much commends, yet are <hi>approved faithfull men, faithfull to the publique inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, for which ſo much blood hath been ſpilt, and treaſure ſpent, ſuch as have been valiant in the field, and ventured their lives in the high places for the liberties of the people, ſuch as have all along in the greateſt Revolutions and Dangers, appeared in their purſes and perſons, for the true intereſt of the Nation: ſuch as have poured forth floods of prayers and tears, for the cauſe of Chriſt; and who cannot be juſtly accuſed for ſitting and voting at Oxon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the whole, this we demand, as the poor ſervants and deſpiſed Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, that upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of this our Reply, he doe either make good the truth of his publique Narrative, and Invective, as to our ſelves, whom he hath particularly named, and reproached, which we are confident he ſhall never doe: or elſe that he doe us right, by making ſome acknowledgement that he hath done us wrong. If he wil doe neither, let him know, who ever he be, that his Letter wil dog him to his death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, and if he obtain not pardon for it in the blood of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> (which from our hearts we wiſh him) it wil ſtand up ſadly againſt him at that day when without ſhall be —<hi>Whoſoever loveth and maketh a lye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides this <hi>Narrative</hi> and <hi>Invective</hi> againſt us, the heat of his indignation vents it ſelfe farther againſt our <hi>Aſso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation.</hi> The Author of this Letter having failed thus as we truſt, in finding <hi>occaſion or fault againſt us concerning the Kingdome:</hi> he endeavours further, to <hi>finde it againſt us, concerning the Law of our God,</hi> attempting to turn it at leaſt to our reproach, that we as <hi>fellow brethren,</hi> yea <hi>as yoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellows, labourers together in the work of the Goſpel,</hi> doe main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a communion and fellowſhip together, for mutual aſſiſtance in our common work. This we cannot but ſay ſomething to, leſt any ſhould be canſleſly byaſſed, by great and empty words, to judge harſhly and falſly of ſome poor unworthy ſervants of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who deſire <hi>to be
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118844:12"/>faithfull.</hi> His words are theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir, by this daies work you may judge of the iſsue and fruit of the Miniſters aſſociation in this County, which may rather be called a ſubtile Combination, then a Chriſtian ſpirituall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, as they mannage it: you will heare of the like procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings in other Counties, eſpecially where this Aſsociation is carried on, the ſame being diviſed as a ſhelter upon a Politique account againſt an approaching ſtorm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Author to wreſt the fault, if there were any, of the late election of members for Parliament upon the <hi>Aſsociation of Miniſters,</hi> is ſo groundleſſe an attempt, as that it proveth onely that the Authour of this Letter being reſolved to take the firſt occaſion, loudly to reproach the <hi>Aſsociation,</hi> caught hold of this in his anger, before ever he conſidered whether it were of weight or no for his purpoſe. The truth is, ſo little influence had our <hi>Aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> upon this <hi>Election,</hi> as that in all the meetings of the Brethren, where we were preſent, never was any the leaſt conſultation about it; we profeſſedly decline in our meetings <hi>all intermedlings in matters of civil concernment,</hi> ſo as that daies work was no more the <hi>iſſue and fruit of our Aſsociation,</hi> then <hi>Tenterden ſteeple</hi> was the cauſe of <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wins ſands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But he ſaith our <hi>Aſsociation</hi> may rather be called <hi>a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile combination, then a Chriſtian ſpiritual Communion, as we manage it.</hi> He ſhould have done wel to have told the world how we doe manage it more like <hi>a ſubtile combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> then <hi>a Chriſtian ſpirituall communion;</hi> and if he could have done it, he would not have ſpared us: but we ſee he hath learnt that principle, <hi>Boldly to calumniate, and then ſomething will ſtick.</hi> And becauſe he wants whereof in particular to accuſe our <hi>actings in this Aſſociation,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he doth quarrel with <hi>out Intentions,</hi> and tels the world <hi>that this Aſsociation was deviſed as a ſhelter upon a Politique account againſt an approaching ſtorm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They riſe above their meaſure doubtleſſe, who take upon them to judge of <hi>heart deſignes</hi> and <hi>intentions,</hi> and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118844:13"/>thereby to condemne actions apparently good, if wel meant. But to ſatisfie the world, and to juſtifie our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, we are not afraid nor aſhamed to lay open the bottome of our deſign in this <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> and how it hath been managed all along. The Brethren are united in Chriſtian love, for mutual aſſiſtance and advice one with another, in that common work of the Miniſtry to which we are called, and thoſe meetings which have been hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to in this Aſſociation, have been managed to the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an comfort and edification of one another, and of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders, <hi>bleſsed be God for it;</hi> and we truſt in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> they ſhall be ſo ever.</p>
            <p>Though our Adverſary be pleaſed to call it <hi>a ſubtile combination,</hi> yet we can <hi>appeale</hi> to him <hi>whom we deſire to ſerve in the Goſpel of his Sonne,</hi> that we intend nothing but <hi>a Spirituall, holy, Chriſtian union</hi> improved (ſo far as our frailty wil permit) in the exerciſe of thoſe uniting graces of <hi>love, humility, ſelf-denial, meekneſſe, and brotherly kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse, for mutuall edification in faith and love which is in Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And if thus to unite be a <hi>griefe</hi> of heart unto any, yet we are ſure it is a <hi>rejoycing</hi> of heart unto many, who <hi>behold how good and how pleaſant it is for brethren thus to dwell even together in unity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>ends</hi> that we propounded to our ſelves, before ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, are ſuch as we are ſure no tongue but ſuch as is <hi>ſet on fire of Hell,</hi> can ſpeak againſt; and the <hi>bleſſed fruits and iſsue</hi> of ſuch an <hi>Aſsociation,</hi> through the good hand of God upon it, will be ſuch as none but ſuch as are too much poſſeſſed with the <hi>ſpirit of envy</hi> can <hi>envy</hi> us the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe thereof. We have long groaned under the evil and the miſchiefe of our diviſions, and we finde that moſt of our jealouſies and jarrings are occaſioned by our <hi>ſtrangeneſle</hi> and <hi>diſtance;</hi> and upon this account our <hi>bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi> at the laſt general meeting, teſtified unanimouſly, and very affectionately, their deſire to have ſuch <hi>brethren,</hi> who differ in matters of <hi>Church conſtitution and order</hi> to joyn in with them, <hi>that as far forth as we are come we may
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118844:13"/>walk together in love and cheerfulneſs by the ſame rule;</hi> and if this might be obtained, we believe it would be <hi>accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Lord,</hi> and a ready way to make a grave wherein to bury for ever much of thoſe <hi>unlively jealouſies, enmity, and unbrotherly bitterneſse</hi> which ſadly appeareth amongſt ſome whom we cannot otherwiſe judge of but that <hi>they are brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Authour ſeems to be poſſeſt with the <hi>ſpirit of jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, and of evil ſurmiſings;</hi> ſince he can get <hi>nothing</hi> againſt us, he will <hi>ſurmiſe</hi> that there is <hi>ſomething;</hi> and if he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not charge our actions, he wil <hi>judge</hi> our <hi>hearts and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and from <hi>thinking</hi> there may be, <hi>concludes</hi> ſurely there is ſomething very blameworthy in us; as the <hi>Jews of Aſia,</hi> ſeeing <hi>Trophimus the Epheſian</hi> with <hi>Paul in the City ſuppoſed that Paul had brought him into the Temple, and cried out, Men of Iſrael help, this is the man that brought Greeks into the Temple, and hath polluted this holy place.</hi> How much this is againſt the <hi>law of love,</hi> he may doe wel to conſider, <hi>for love thinketh no evil.</hi> It is ſtoried of <hi>Cambyſes,</hi> he did but <hi>dream his <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> King of Perſia, and for this he put him to death:</hi> ſo this man doth but <hi>dream of plots and deſignes of a ſubtile combination, and a politique device,</hi> and he preſently <hi>concludes,</hi> ſo it is: and what he would do unto us if he had power in his hand it is eaſie to judge; even that which (to uſe his own words) <hi>would make our cares to tingle, and our hearts to ake:</hi> which leads us from his Invective to his threatnings.</p>
            <p>He tels us of an <hi>approaching ſtorm;</hi> and again, <hi>as it was with the Prelates in entring their Proteſtation in the former Parliament, they prepared a Rod to whip themſelves with, and digged a pit wherein they themſelves did fall: ſo will theſe men doe, that which they have deſigned for upholding their corrupt intereſt, will be the Ruine thereof: and again thoſe rigid and fooliſh men will not ſee the hand of God which is gone out againſt them, but goe on in their vain waies of oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, notwithſtanding they have been ſo often diſappinted:
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118844:14"/>yea the work of the Lord ſhall proſper, and God will ere long ſeparate his faithfull Miniſters and ſervants from this corrupt ſelf-ſeeking generation of men.</hi> And again, <hi>though good men ſhould be ſilent and ſit ſtill, yet the Lord himſelfe will ſhortly avenge the cauſe of his people, and bring deliverance in a way which we think not of, which will make the ears of ſome to tingle, and their hearts ake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In all theſe paſſages he doth threaten the Miniſters ſhrewdly, with what is comming upon them, and no marvil, <hi>Quicquid ſperamus facile Credimus;</hi> he hopes to ſee the downfal of the Miniſtry, and ſo eaſily believes it, and it may be thinks it will never be well till it be ſo. It is no new thing to meet with peremptory predictions of the ruine and downfal of the Miniſtry, which yet through the goodneſſe of our God have fallen to the ground without expected accompliſhment; and it is no ſmal mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy that God hath beaten out the <hi>Teeth</hi> of our <hi>Maligners;</hi> that they only can <hi>bark</hi> and not <hi>bite,</hi> that their <hi>tongues</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and not their <hi>hands</hi> can reach us: yet the world may ſee they doe what they can, and therefore the Author here doth not ſo much <hi>Prophecy</hi> of, as <hi>Project our ruine,</hi> by ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring us <hi>odious</hi> both to the <hi>People,</hi> by ranking us with the <hi>Prelates,</hi> and alſo to his <hi>Highneſse and his Army,</hi> by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking them againſt us, as <hi>being of that ſort of men who have cauſed the late broiles, and will yet againe imbroile the Nation in blood if God in mercy prevents not:</hi> In which he deales with us and the <hi>reſt of the Clergy of this Nation,</hi> (as he ſtiles them) as the <hi>Perſecuters</hi> did in the <hi>Primitive</hi> times with the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> they put the bodies of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans into the skins of wilde beaſts, and then ſet wilde beaſts upon them for to tear them, ſo he puts us into the ſhapes of his own conceits, of his own apprehenſions, and his own ſlanders of purpoſe to make us ugly, and to render us vile and contemptible, that ſo the more eaſie way may be made for our ruine: But our <hi>truſt</hi> is in our <hi>God who knowes our hearts,</hi> that he will in due time cleare our Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency againſt thoſe malicious ſuggeſtions, and make it
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118844:14"/>appeare to his <hi>Highneſſe and his Army,</hi> and to the <hi>whole Nation,</hi> that as poor weak <hi>ſervants of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> we deſire joyntly to promote the <hi>Kingdome of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>proſperity of the Commonwealth</hi> in which we live.</p>
            <p>But he tells us <hi>we will not ſee the hand of God which is gone out againſt us, but go on in our vaine wayes of oppoſition not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding we have been ſo often diſappointed.</hi> To this we anſwer.</p>
            <p>We feare we have been all of us too unobſervant of the <hi>Lords hand,</hi> both of <hi>chaſtiſement</hi> and <hi>mercy</hi> too when it is lifted up over us, but ſurely it is our blindneſſe, or elſe the Lords hand hath not been altogether ſtretched out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>contemned Miniſtry of this Nation</hi> in Judgement, of latter times: we think there was a time not long ſince, when many ſadly feared, and others ſtrongly hoped that the deſpiſed, diſowned Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> ſhould quite have ſhaken hands with their maintenance and Miniſtry together, and had done ſo, had not the Lord then appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the Mount wonderouſly, and unexpectedly, for the reſcuing his poor ſervants. We have often thought it our duty to acknowledge this work of God, and to walke humbly, carefully, and thankfully before the Lord in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard hereof. Our comfort and hope at the worſt was, that our <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> hath <hi>his Stars</hi> of all magnitudes <hi>in his right hand,</hi> and that unleſſe he <hi>remove the Candleſtick</hi> he will continue <hi>his Stars</hi> amongſt us, how much ſoever they be clouded by the reproaches of many adverſaries; and our hope and comfort ſtill is, that we have the <hi>ſame Lord who hath delivered us,</hi> upon whom <hi>to truſt that he will yet deliver us;</hi> And we heartily bleſſe God for the <hi>inſtruments</hi> under him of our <hi>deliverance,</hi> and we hope that they ſhall never have cauſe to repent, they nor their poſterity, that they have <hi>reſcued a poor deſpiſed Miniſtry from rapine and ruine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Author ſeemes to be deſirous the world ſhould think that he is no enemy to the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> but only to ſuch as are <hi>corrupt, ſelf-ſeekers, buſie-bodies,</hi> and therefore,</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:118844:15"/>
            <p n="1">1. He makes an honourable mention of ſome whom he calls <hi>faithful Miniſters,</hi> and ſaith, <hi>God will e're long ſeparate his faithful Miniſters and ſervants from this corrupt ſelf-ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king generation of men;</hi> But if <hi>this corrupt ſelf-ſeeking gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of men</hi> be the <hi>whole Clergy of the Nation,</hi> as he ſeems all along to carry it, then they ſtand all without the reach of his <hi>charity,</hi> and cannot any of them obtaine ſo much from him, as to hope that they are in the number of <hi>Gods faithful Miniſters and ſervants,</hi> yet we doubt not but that even amongſt thoſe whom he calls, <hi>this corrupt ſelf-ſeeking generation, God</hi> hath many <hi>precious ones</hi> even amongſt thoſe whom he accounts as <hi>the filth and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he off-ſcowring of all things;</hi> Many <hi>faithful ones</hi> whoſe <hi>Miniſterial abilities, admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſucceſse in winning ſoules to God,</hi> diligent <hi>and powerful Preaching, ſound and wholſome doctrine, peaceable demeanour,</hi> and <hi>holy and exemplary converſation</hi> doth diſtinguiſh them and <hi>ſeparate them</hi> from a <hi>corrupt ſelf-ſeekin<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> generation:</hi> and this <hi>ſeparation</hi> we doubt not but God hath already made in the hearts of thoſe who are truly ſenſible of the many gracious workes the Lord hath wrought by them, and who for their <hi>workes ſake doe account them worthy of double honour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. He prayes <hi>that God would forgive theſe men, for they cauſe the Miniſtry of Chriſt to be evil ſpoken of, and to ſtinke in the noſtrils of people who doe but deride them as a company of vain buſie-bodies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who would have expected after all this dirt caſt upon us by the Author, to have found in him ſo deep a ſenſe of the <hi>reproaches caſt upon the Miniſtry of Chriſt?</hi> but alas, a few good words in the cloſe will not be ſufficient to waſh off the guilt of all his former reproachings and revilings: how much himſelf doth ſtand in need of the benefit of this prayer, will appear to the judicious reader, if we do make a very little alteration in it; <hi>God forgive this man for cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> (as much as in him is) <hi>the Miniſtry of Chriſt to be evil ſpoken of, and to ſtinke in the noſtrils of the people</hi> by his <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riding of them as a company of vaine buſie-bodies, for their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118844:15"/>of that which no law of God or man doth forbid unto them.</hi> And we would deſire the Author of this Letter to examine his own conſcience in ſecret, upon this Interrogatory, how tender ſoever he ſeemes to be of the reputation of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry that he would not <hi>have it to ſtink in the noſtrils of the people,</hi> whether that which troubles him at the very heart be not becauſe he ſees us, and other poor ſervants of Jeſus Chriſt, notwithſtanding all open and ſecret counter wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, ſtill to retaine a high place both as to our perſons and Miniſtery in the love and eſteem of multitudes who truly feare the Lord; however it will ſound in his cares, we ſhall take the boldneſſe in all <hi>humility and thankefulneſs</hi> to our <hi>good God</hi> for his <hi>abundant kindneſse towards his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy ſervants,</hi> to aſſure him that the deſpiſed Miniſtry and Miniſters of the Goſpel in this Nation, even at this day doe finds (bleſſed b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Lord) much <hi>love</hi> in the hearts of very many who <hi>walk humbly and cloſely with the Lord their God;</hi> nor doe theſe ſervants of God diſcover any more eminent effect of the <hi>hard ſpeeches</hi> which are in <hi>word</hi> and <hi>Print</hi> uttered againſt them by <hi>bitter men</hi> of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſpirits and intereſts, then the <hi>blowing up</hi> of the <hi>affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of many of Gods people to a ſtronger <hi>flame of love</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them and their <hi>Miniſtry;</hi> which therefore we hope the Lord will <hi>teach</hi> and <hi>ſtrengthen</hi> his weake ſervants with greater <hi>faithfulneſſe to fulfil to his own glory, the ſtopping of the mouthes of their enraged adverſaries,</hi> and the <hi>good of the poor of his flock who wait on him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are glad to hear that the Author of this Letter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks himſelf at laſt of the <hi>Chriſtian weapons of Faith Hope, Patience, Prayers, and Teares;</hi> it was our hard lot to fall into his h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nds whileſt he was making uſe of other more ſharpe weapons; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 57. <hi>v.</hi> 4. yet if he and thoſe of his party, of whom he ſpeaketh, be in good earneſt to ſtand to thoſe ſpiritual weapons only, for the time to come we ſhall deſire to make uſe of no other; and if we fight on both ſides with theſe Armes, there may at laſt be hope that we may be brought together into the bond of truth and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118844:16"/>Chriſtian love, to ſerve our God with one conſent ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his bleſſed word.</p>
            <p>All the revenge we will take of our accuſer for his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious dealing with us, ſhall be to joyne him with our ſelves in our prayers to the Lord (though poſſibly he may ſcorne the motion, as not thinking that we have any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with God) that he would <hi>deliver both him and us from every evil worke, and keep us to his heavenly Kingdome to whom be glory for ever,</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:118844:16"/>
            <head>Books newly printed by <hi>Ralph Smith,</hi> viz.</head>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Dicksons</hi> Expoſition on the whole Book of the <hi>Pſalms</hi> in three Books.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Chriſtian Charter,</hi> ſhewing the priviledge of Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers in this life, and in the life to come: by Mr. <hi>Watſon</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Stephen Walbroke;</hi> the third Edition, much enlarged.</p>
            <p>Alſo, Mr. <hi>Watſons</hi> Art of Divine contentment; the ſecond Edition.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hutchinſons</hi> Expoſition on the ſix ſmall Prophets, viz. <hi>Obadiah, Jonah, Micah, Nahum, Habakkuk,</hi> and <hi>Zepha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hutchinſons</hi> Expoſition on the three laſt Prophets, <hi>viz. Haggai, Zechariah, Malachi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Expoſition on the whole book of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> by that late learned and pious Divine, Mr. <hi>John Cotton</hi> Paſtor of <hi>Boſtock</hi> in <hi>New England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Sermon of Mr. <hi>Simon Aſh</hi> at the funerall of Mr. <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiah Whitaker.</hi> Together with a Narrative of his pious life. The ſecond Edition, many other Poems and Elegies added.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
